<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Operating System Fundamentals">
  
	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Software Defined Network (SDN) Controller Essential Security Requirements</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership (NIAP)</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>1.0</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>29 November 2021</issuedate>
		<approver/>
		<supercedes/>
	</intro>

	<section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
		This document describes a core set of high-level fundamental 
		security requirements expected of any Software Defined Networking
		(SDN) Controller for use in an enterprise. It is intended to 
		provide a minimal, baseline set of requirements which can be built
		upon by future revisions to provide an overall set of security 
		solutions for an enterprise network.
		<p/>
		SDN Controllers are one of many components of an SDN networking 
		architecture. See below diagram.
		<p/>
	
		<figure entity="images/sdncontroller.png" 
			title="SDN Controller in relation to the SDN Planes"
			id="sdn-controller"
		/>
		<p/>
		An SDN Controller is a central and vital component of what 
		constitutes an SDN system and is available as a logical or a 
		physical device. An SDN Controller manages and distributes network
		policies, collects routing and payload information from the Data
		Plane, and interfaces with user applications in the Management
		Plane. Each of the planes in an SDN system is composed of multiple
		logical or physical components. SDN Controllers logically 
		centralize the network intelligence and state in the Control 
		Plane. 
		<p/>
		For clarity the following definitions are provided:
		<ul>
			<li>
				The Control Plane is a logical entity that receives 
				instructions or requirements from the SDN Application 
				layer through its northbound interface and relays them to
				the Data Plane through its southbound interface. The 
				Controller extracts information about the network from 
				the Data Plane and communicates back to the SDN 
				Application Layer with an abstract view of the network,
				including statistics and events about what is happening.
			</li>
			<li>
				The Data Plane (or SDN Network Devices) controls the 
				forwarding and data processing capabilities for the 
				network. This includes forwarding and processing of the
				data path.
			</li>
			<li>
				The Management Plane (or SDN Applications Layer) is 
				composed of programs that communicate behaviors and 
				needed resources with the SDN Controller via application
				programming interfaces (APIs). In addition, the 
				applications can build an abstracted view of the network
				by collecting information from the Controller for 
				decision-making purposes. These applications could 
				include networking management, analytics, or business
				applications used to run large data centers. For example,
				an analytics application might be built to recognize 
				suspicious network activity for security purposes. The 
				Management Plane is sometimes also referred to as the 
				Orchestration Layer.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	<section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
	  <ul>
	  	<li>
	  		SDN controller as a standalone physical device.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		SDN controller as a virtual device.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		SDN Controller (standalone or virtual) with management 
	  		capabilities.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		A cluster of SDN Controllers (standalone or virtual).
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An SDN Controller for hyper-converge consisting of an amalgam of computing resources in a single unit for storage centric, server centric or even hybrid (storage-server) workloads.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		The intent is that an SDN Controller satisfying these 
	  		requirements will “do no harm” on a network. Rather than 
	  		providing any explicit security functionality, compliant 
	  		SDN Controllers simply ensure:
	  	</li>
	  	<ul>
	  		<li>
	  			They can be remotely managed in a secure manner.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Any software/firmware updates are from a trusted source.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Any interfaces to applications, VMs, and other devices are
	  			trusted (zone of trust).
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			All suspect events are reported.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Logical or physical separation of the Control and Data 
	  			Planes.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Logical or physical separation of the Control and Management 
	  			Planes.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Protect data collected and distributed by the Control Plane
	  			to the Data Plane such as flow tables and configurations.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Protect data collected and distributed by the Control Plane 
	  			to the Management Plane such as auditable events and 
	  			traffic/packet statistics.
	  		</li>
	  		<li>
	  			Protect data collected, distributed and shared within the 
	  			Control Plane such as when multiple SDN controllers exist 
	  			in the architecture.
	  		</li>
	  	</ul>
	  </ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
    	  <ul>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Any network-facing management interfaces, including traffic
    	  		to and from the SDN Controller, and any critical data 
    	  		(e.g., audit data).
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		SDN Controller software/firmware.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Data stored locally by the SDN Controller (e.g. Policy, 
    	  		flow control, etc.).
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Configuration and reboot data, including any policy made 
    	  		part of the boot configuration.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Authentication credentials such as keys and passwords.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Northbound, Southbound and East/West channels/connections.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Any stored updates intended for SDN Devices.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>	
     	  		SDN switch configuration and reboot data stored in the SDN 
     	  		Controller.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Traffic/packet statistics.
    	  	</li>
    	  	<li>
    	  		Audit information.
    	  	</li>
    	  </ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess"> 
	  <ul>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can send arbitrary packets to network interfaces. 
	  	</li>
	  	<li> 
	  		An attacker can intercept and arbitrarily modify or drop 
	  		packets within existing traffic flows. 
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can impersonate the role of the SDN controller in the network. An attacker can impersonate the role of another SDN controller in the network.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can leverage the lack of an established standard 
	  		for communication between the SDN Controller and other 
	  		components in an SDN network and so taking advantage of 
	  		interoperability or under-tested protocols
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can leverage any automation functionality to cause
	  		the most damage before being discovered.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can intercept and arbitrarily affect communications
	  		between an SDN Controller and any northbound applications 
	  		and/or components. 
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can intercept and arbitrarily affect communications 
	  		between SDN Controllers, east/west communication.
	  	</li>
	  	<li>
	  		An attacker can intercept and arbitrarily affect communications 
	  		between the SDN Controller and any switches under its control, 
	  		southbound communication.
	  	</li>
	  </ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Evaluation Boundary" id="evaluationboundary"> 
		<ul>
			<li>
				In the case of a physical standalone SDN Controller device,
				the hardware, firmware and software of the device define 
				the evaluation boundary.  
			</li>
			<li> 
				In the case of a Virtual SDN Controller, the software of 
				the Virtual Machine (VM) defines the evaluation boundary.
			</li>
			<li>
				All of the security functionality is contained and executed 
				within the evaluation boundary of the SDN Controller. 
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>			
	
	<section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
		The following are the essential security requirements that are 
		expected to be implemented by an SDN Controller. Note that these
		security requirements are conditional on that functionality being 
		present. For example, an SDN Controller that does not include any
		management functionality is considered to satisfy any security
		requirements that pertain to the secure use of management features.
		<p/>
		Any other conditional requirements that depend on whether or not
		the product implements a certain capability are listed in the
		“Optional Extensions” section below.
		<ul>
			<li>
				The remote administration and audit functions shall use cryptographic algorithms to encrypt and protect communication, 
				following guidelines and recommendations from NIST SP 800-131A and its future updates to cryptographic standards and algorithms.
			</li>
			<li>
				All communications with other SDN controllers and their components must be protected and authenticated using (but not limited to)
				secure communication protocols [TLS 1.2 or higher, SSH], mutual authentication [Certificates and Public Key Infrastructure, Pre-shared Keys],
				access control [RBAC], and cryptographic algorithms [NIST SP 800-131A]. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller must have the ability to continuously monitor and log activities, as well as audit administrative actions which may include
				but not limited to CRUD (Create, Read, Update, Delete) operations on managed devices in the fabric, logical network groups
				(including VLANs, VXLANs, and IP subnets/prefixes), routing table updates, and loss of communications to resources. The SDN controller should
				log detailed user actions, including the methods used (API, WebUI, CLI), to provide context on changes, thereby enhancing the system's traceability
				and security.  
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller shall provide an authentication mechanism for any users/administrators, as well as the device/VM itself that
				comply with NIST SP 800-63 and ISO/IEC 27001 and SO/IEC 27002. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller is required to implement an authorization system for any users/administrators, as well as the device/VM itself, 
				employing a RBAC or ABAC model that adheres to the principle of least privilege and that comply with NIST SP 800-53 / NIST SP 800-162. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller shall provide a cryptographic means to validate the source of updates to be installed on the device/VM.    
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller will enforce a policy requiring the modification of any default passwords or other credentials immediately
				upon installation. Additionally, it will compel users to create complex passwords that comply with NIST 800 63B. Beyond password
				complexity, the controller will also support multi-factor authentication (MFA) that comply NIST SP 800-63B. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller shall protect keys, key material, and authentication credentials from unauthorized disclosure.  
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller requires design and construction that ensures it remains operational and effective amidst cybersecurity
				threats ranging from but not limited to Malware, MitM, DoS, SQL injection, APTs, Fuzzing attacks, and HTTP-based vulnerabilities
				with robustness to maintain performance under stress and resilience for rapid recovery from attacks, safeguarding network integrity
				and minimizing disruptions. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller shall provide self-tests to ensure the security functions it implements are operating correctly.   
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
		<ul>
			<li>
				The SDN Controller relies on a trustworthy computing platform for its execution and it is assumed that the 
				platform has not been compromised prior to the installation of the SDN Controller. 
				For example, the effectiveness of non-interference and strict information flow control 
				of an SDN controller will typically depend on the effectiveness of an underlying (embedded) operating system or hypervisor to provide non-interference and controlled information flow.
			</li>
			<li>
				The administrator of the underlying platform or SDN 
				Controller is not careless, willfully negligent or hostile,
				and administers the software within compliance of the 
				approved enterprise security policy. 
			</li>
			<li>
				Physical security appropriate to the value of the SDN 
				Controller and the data it contains is provided. An SDN Controller is protected from physical attacks by the wider environment.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Optional Extensions" id="extensions"> 
		The following requirements may already be realized in some products
		in this technology class, but the ESR is not mandating these 
		capabilities exist in “baseline” level product:
		<ul>
			<li>
				Automatic response to certain security events.
			</li>
			<li>
				Validation of patches and updates intended for data plane 
				SDN Devices - as an add-on to any validation performed in
				the switch and not as an alternative.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Objective Requirements" id="objective"> 
		Requirements specified here specify security-relevant behavior 
		that is not expected to be realized currently in SDN Controllers, 
		but capabilities that may be mandated in future versions of the 
		ESR and resulting cPPs.
		<ul>
			<li>
				The device shall have internal security features to make
				the device more resilient to security breaches. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The device shall provide two-factor authentication 
				natively on the device (i.e., does not rely on a 
				separate device to provide this capability). 
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Outside the TOE's Scope" id="outsidescope">
	    <ul>
			<li>
				Specific security functionality that is not global to all 
				SDN Controllers (e.g. firewall, load balancers) as these 
				will be specified in other ESRs. 
			</li>
	    	<li>
	    		Examination of data plane content (including Virus scanning
	    		and email scanning).
	    	</li>
			<li>
				Intrusion detection/prevention capabilities. 
			</li>
			<li>
				Network Address Translation (NAT) as a security function. 
			</li>
			<li>
				The hardware or firmware of the underlying platform 
				(virtualized SDN Controller only).
			</li>
	    	<li>
	    		The host operating system or runtime environment 
	    		(virtualized SDN Controller only).
	    	</li>
	    	<li>
	    		The TOE shall not address other objects belonging in the
	    		Data Plane, even if they are delivered as part of the 
	    		product installation process.
	    	</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
</ESR>
