<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xsl-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/xsl/module/module2html.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="../transforms/schemas/CCModule.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<Module name="PP-Module for Software-Defined Networking Controller" boilerplate="yes" target-product="Software-Defined Networking Controller" xmlns="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:sec="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1/section">
  <PPReference>
    <ReferenceTable>
      <PPVersion>1.0</PPVersion>
      <PPAuthor>National Information Assurance Partnership</PPAuthor>
      <PPPubDate>2026-04-20</PPPubDate>
      <Keywords>SDN; software-defined networking</Keywords>
    </ReferenceTable>
  </PPReference>
  <RevisionHistory>
    <entry>
      <version>1.0</version>
      <date>2026-04-20</date>
      <subject>Initial release</subject>
    </entry>
  </RevisionHistory>
  <pp-preferences/>
  <sec:Introduction>
    <sec:Overview title="Overview">
      The scope of this Protection Profile Module (PP-Module) is to describe the security functionality of a software-defined network (SDN) controller in terms of
      <xref g="CC"/>
      and to define functional and assurance requirements for such products.
      <h:p/>
      An SDN controller is a central component of an SDN system and is available as a logical or physical device. An SDN controller manages and distributes network
            policies, collects network routing and payload information from the control and data planes, and interfaces with user applications in the management plane for
            functions such as configuration and logging. Each of the planes in an SDN system is composed of multiple logical or physical components. The SDN controller logically
            separates the data plane from the control plane and centralizes control which enhances network flexibility and scalability through more efficient network management.
      <h:p/>
      This PP-Module is intended for use with the following Base-PP.
      <h:ul>
        <h:li>collaborative Protection Profile for Network Devices, Version 4.0</h:li>
      </h:ul>
      This Base-PP is valid because an SDN controller is a specific implementation of a network device. Specifically, an SDN controller is one of many components of an SDN networking architecture. An SDN controller manages and distributes network policies, collects routing and payload information from the data plane, and interfaces with user applications in the management plane. Each of the planes in an SDN system is composed of multiple logical or physical components. SDN controllers logically centralize the network intelligence and state in the control plane.
    </sec:Overview>
    <tech-terms>
      <suppress>Functional Package,Extended Package</suppress>
      <term full="Administrator">An administrator is responsible for management activities, including setting policies that are applied by the enterprise on the operating system. This administrator
	       could be acting remotely through a management server, from which the system receives configuration policies. An administrator can enforce settings on the system 
	       which cannot be overridden by non-administrator users.</term>
      <term full="Application">Software that runs on a platform and performs tasks on behalf of the user or owner of the platform, as well as its supporting documentation.</term>
      <term full="Application Programming Interface" abbr="API">A specification of routines, data structures, object classes, and variables that allows an application to make use of services provided by another software
	       component, such as a library. APIs are often provided for a set of libraries included with the platform.</term>
      <term full="Credential">Data that establishes the identity of a user (e.g., a cryptographic key or password).</term>
      <term full="Control Plane">A logical entity that receives instructions or requirements from the SDN application layer through its northbound interface and relays them to the data plane through
          its southbound interface. The controller extracts information about the network from the data plane and communicates back to the SDN application layer with an 
          abstract view of the network, including statistics and events about what is happening.</term>
      <term full="Data Plane">Controls the forwarding and data processing capabilities for the network. This includes forwarding and processing of the data path.</term>
      <term full="Management Plane">Composed of programs that communicate behaviors and needed resources with the SDN controller via APIs.
        In addition, the applications can build an abstracted view of the network by collecting information from the controller for decision-making purposes. These 
        applications could include networking management, analytics, or business applications used to run large data centers. For example, an analytics application might be
        built to recognize suspicious network activity for security purposes. This is sometimes also referred to as the Orchestration Layer.</term>
      <term full="Northbound">Communications between an SDN and applications in the management plane.</term>
      <term full="Southbound">Communications between an SDN and network devices in the data plane.</term>
      <term full="Deterministic Random Bit Generator" abbr="DRBG"/>
      <term full="Hypertext Transfer Protocol" abbr="HTTP"/>
      <term full="Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure" abbr="HTTPS"/>
      <term full="Internet Protocol" abbr="IP"/>
      <term full="Information Technology" abbr="IT"/>
      <term full="Office of Management and Budget" abbr="OMB"/>
      <term full="Operating System" abbr="OS"/>
      <term full="Role-Based Access Control" abbr="RBAC"/>
      <term full="Random Bit Generator" abbr="RBG"/>
      <term full="Representational State Transfer" abbr="REST"/>
      <term full="Request for Comment" abbr="RFC"/>
      <term full="Software-Defined Networking" abbr="SDN"/>
      <term full="Transport Layer Security" abbr="TLS"/>
      <term full="Universal Serial Bus" abbr="USB"/>
      <term full="Virtual Machine" abbr="VM"/>
      <term full="Virtual Private Network" abbr="VPN"/>
      <term full="Exclusive Or" abbr="XOR"/>
    </tech-terms>
    <sec:Compliant_Targets_of_Evaluation>
      A conformant TOE decouples its data and control planes such that data traffic and control traffic are restricted
      to their respective planes. It also enforces centralization of control so that all components of the SDN environment
      are under its control. This can expand across multiple distributed controllers for large, complex, or geographically
      dispersed networks. Compliant TOEs will implement the following functionality.
      <h:ul>
        <h:li>Ability to support secure remote administration.</h:li>
        <h:li>Ability to apply software or firmware updates from a trusted source.</h:li>
        <h:li>Secure interfaces to remote entities such as applications, VMs, and other devices (zone of trust).</h:li>
        <h:li>Reporting of all security-relevant events.</h:li>
        <h:li>Logical separation of the management, control, and data planes.</h:li>
        <h:li>Protection of data that is collected by the control plane and distributed to the data plane, such as flow tables and configuration.</h:li>
        <h:li>Protection of data that is collected by the control plane and distributed to the management plane, such as auditable events and traffic or packet statistics.</h:li>
        <h:li>Protection of data that is collected, distributed, and shared within the control plane, such as when multiple SDN controllers exist in the architecture.</h:li>
      </h:ul>
      <sec:TOE_Boundary>
        The TOE boundary for an SDN controller is one or more physical or virtual devices. An SDN controller may be a distributed TOE, as defined by the Base-PP.
        <h:ul>
          <h:li>In a physical standalone SDN controller device, the device's hardware, firmware, and software define the evaluation boundary.</h:li>
          <h:li>In a virtual SDN controller, the software of the Virtual Machine (VM) defines the evaluation boundary. The Base-PP includes guidance on whether the evaluation boundary includes the virtualization system on which the VM runs.</h:li>
          <h:li>All security functionality is contained and executed within the evaluation boundary of the SDN controller.</h:li>
        </h:ul>
        <h:p>
          The following figure shows the logical position of the SDN controller between the management and data planes within the SDN infrastructure. This is a simplified diagram of the TOE's position in an SDN deployment. Other dependencies that are necessary to meet security requirements, such as an audit server, remote management interface, or source of certificate revocation information are not shown.
          <figure entity="images/sdncontroller.png" title="High-Level SDN Representation" id="sdn-toe"/>
        </h:p>
        <h:p>
          The following elements of an SDN controller are outside the scope of this PP-Module and are therefore considered to be non-interfering with respect to its security, even if they are included as part of a compliant product.
          <h:ul>
            <h:li>Examination of data plane content, such as virus or email scanning.</h:li>
            <h:li>Intrusion detection or prevention capabilities.</h:li>
            <h:li>Network Address Translation (NAT) as a security function.</h:li>
            <h:li>If the TOE boundary is a standalone virtual machine, the hardware or firmware of the underlying platform.</h:li>
            <h:li>If the TOE boundary is a standalone virtual machine, the host operating system or runtime environment.</h:li>
            <h:li>Specific security functionality that is not global to all SDN controllers (e.g., firewall, load balancing).</h:li>
            <h:li>Other objects belonging in the data plane.</h:li>
          </h:ul>
        </h:p>
        <h:p>Other PP-Modules may exist to allow for other functions such as these to be defined as part of the TOE boundary.</h:p>
      </sec:TOE_Boundary>
    </sec:Compliant_Targets_of_Evaluation>
    <sec:Use_Cases>
      Requirements in this PP-Module are designed to address the security problems in at least the following use cases. These use cases are 
        intentionally very broad, as many specific use cases exist for an SDN controller. These use cases may also overlap with one another. An SDN controller's 
        functionality may even be effectively extended by privileged applications installed on it. However, these are out of scope of this PP-Module.
      <usecases>
        <usecase title="Physical Device" id="standalonephysdev">
          <description>The TOE is one or more physical appliances that provide SDN controller functionality. The TOE boundary includes the entire software and firmware running on these appliances; a software-only device where the boundary does not include the underlying operating system is not a valid use case.</description>
        </usecase>
        <usecase title="Virtual Device" id="virtualdev">
          <description>The TOE is a virtual machine that provides SDN controller functionality. The TOE boundary is either limited to the virtual machine or includes the hypervisor and underlying physical hardware, depending on whether or not the hypervisor may include virtual machines that are not part of the SDN controller or if the hypervisor itself includes functionality necessary for the TOE to implement the required security functionality. As with the physical device use case above, the TOE boundary for a virtual device must include an entire virtual machine and not just a collection of applications or services running on an environmental operating system.</description>
        </usecase>
        <usecase title="Cluster (stand-alone or virtual)" id="standorvirtcluster">
          <description>Regardless of whether the TOE is physical, virtual, or both, it may include multiple distinct instances (i.e., multiple connected physical appliances or VMs) that are combined into a distributed cluster.</description>
        </usecase>
      </usecases>
    </sec:Use_Cases>
  </sec:Introduction>
  <sec:Conformance_Claims boilerplate="no">
    <CClaimsInfo cc-version="cc-2022r1" cc-approach="direct-rationale">
      <cc-st-conf>exact</cc-st-conf>
      <cc-pt2-conf>extended</cc-pt2-conf>
      <cc-pt3-conf>conformant</cc-pt3-conf>
      <cc-pp-conf>
        <PP-cc-ref>collaborative Protection Profile for Network Devices, v4.0</PP-cc-ref>
      </cc-pp-conf>
      <cc-pp-config-with>
        <Mod-cc-ref>collaborative Protection Profile Module for Stateful Traffic Filter Firewalls,
            version 2.0</Mod-cc-ref>
        <Mod-cc-ref>PP-Module for Authentication Servers, version 2.0</Mod-cc-ref>
        <Mod-cc-ref>PP-Module for MACsec Ethernet Encryption, version 2.0</Mod-cc-ref>
        <Mod-cc-ref>PP-Module for VPN Gateways, version 2.0</Mod-cc-ref>
      </cc-pp-config-with>
      <cc-pkg-claim>
        <FP-cc-ref conf="conformant">Functional Package for TLS, version 2.1</FP-cc-ref>
        <FP-cc-ref conf="conformant">Functional Package for Secure Shell, version 2.0</FP-cc-ref>
      </cc-pkg-claim>
    </CClaimsInfo>
  </sec:Conformance_Claims>
  <!-- 3.0 Security Problem Definition-->
  <sec:Security_Problem_Definition>
    The security problem is described in terms of the threats that the TOE is expected to address, assumptions about 
		the operational environment, and any organizational security policies that the OS is expected to enforce.
    <!-- 3.1 Threats -->
    <sec:Threats>
      <threats>
        <threat name="T.INSECURE_NORTHBOUND_API">
          <description>A malicious user or process may invoke insecure application programming interfaces (APIs) to inject malicious code to the TOE on a northbound interface or to
            retrieve sensitive information from it. Executing improper or unauthorized API functions or providing malicious input to achieve unintended or improper results from
            proper or authorized API functions can compromise network services. This can also result in sensitive data leakage.</description>
          <!-- New mapping to build updated threat mapping table. -->
          <addressed-by>FAU_GEN.1/SDN</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by generating audit records of activities performed on or by the TSF that could affect the northbound interface.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FDP_ACC.1</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by enforcing access control on the APIs offered by the TOE.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FDP_ACF.1</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by defining the mechanism for how API access control is enforced.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FMT_API_EXT.1</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by allowing API templates to be defined against objects based on a set of defined 
          rules.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FMT_MOF.1/SDN</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by limiting the ability to modify API functions.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FMT_SMF.1/SDN</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by identifying the management functions subject to access restrictions.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FMT_SMR.2/SDN</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by defining a role separation mechanism for administrators to enforce least privilege.</rationale>
          <addressed-by>FTP_ITC.1 (modified from ND PP)</addressed-by>
          <rationale>Mitigates the threat by defining the trusted communications channel used for SDN functionality.</rationale>
        </threat>
      </threats>
    </sec:Threats>
    <!-- 3.2 Assumptions -->
    <sec:Assumptions>
      All assumptions from the Base-PP also apply to the TOE’s environment when it
      includes this PP‐Module in its conformance claims.
      <assumptions/>
    </sec:Assumptions>
    <!-- 3.3 Organizational Security Policies -->
    <sec:Organizational_Security_Policies>
      <OSPs/>
    </sec:Organizational_Security_Policies>
  </sec:Security_Problem_Definition>
  <!-- 4.0 Security Objectives -->
  <sec:Security_Objectives>
    <!-- 4.1 Security Objectives for the TOE -->
    <!-- 4.2 Security Objctives for the Operational Environment -->
    <sec:Security_Objectives_for_the_Operational_Environment>All environmental security objectives from the Base-PP also apply to the TOE’s environment when it
      includes this PP‐Module in its conformance claims.</sec:Security_Objectives_for_the_Operational_Environment>
    <!-- 4.3 Security Objectives Rationale -->
  </sec:Security_Objectives>
  <!-- 5.0 Security Requirements -->
  <sec:Security_Requirements title="Security Requirements">
    <!-- 5.1 ND PP Security Functional Requirements Direction -->
    <base-pp id="ND" name="Network Device" product="Network Device" short="ND" version="4.0" plural="Network Devices">
      <url>https://old.niap-ccevs.org/MMO/PP/CPP_ND_V4.0.pdf</url>
      <cPP/>
      <!-- 5.1.1 Modified SFRs -->
      <modified-sfrs>
        <section title="Class FTP: Trusted Path/Channels" id="nd-m-ftp">
          <!-- FTP_ITC.1 Inter-TSF Trusted Channel -->
          <base-sfr-spec cc-id="ftp_itc.1" id="nd-ftp-itc-1" title="Inter-TSF Trusted Channel">
            <consistency-rationale>This PP-Module expands the Base-PP SFR to define additional entities for trusted channels.</consistency-rationale>
            <description>
              <h:p>This SFR has been modified from its definition in the NDcPP to define external interfaces to environmental entities that are particular to this specific
                    technology type.</h:p>
              <h:p>The text of the requirement is replaced with:</h:p>
              <h:p>
                <h:b>FTP_ITC.1.1</h:b>
                The TSF shall be capable of using [<h:b>selection:</h:b>
                <h:i>IPsec, SSH as defined in the Functional Package for SSH, TLS as defined
                      in the Functional Package for TLS, DTLS as defined in the Functional Package for TLS, HTTPS</h:i>] to provide a trusted communication channel between
                    itself and authorized IT entities supporting the following capabilities: audit server,
                <h:b>northbound components, southbound components,</h:b>
                [<h:b>selection:</h:b>
                <h:i>
                  authentication server,
                  <h:b>external east/west components</h:b>
                  [<h:b>assignment:</h:b>
                  other capabilities], no other
                      capabilities
                </h:i>] that is logically distinct from other
                  communication channels and provides assured identification of its endpoints
                  and protection of the channel data from disclosure and detection of modification of the channel data.
              </h:p>
              <h:p>
                <h:b>FTP_ITC.1.2</h:b>
                The TSF shall permit [<h:b>selection:</h:b>
                <h:i> the TSF, the authorized IT entities</h:i>] to initiate
                    communication via the trusted channel.
              </h:p>
              <h:p>
                <h:b>FTP_ITC.1.3</h:b>
                The TSF shall initiate communication via the trusted channel for
                    [<h:b>assignment:</h:b>
                <h:i>list of services for which the TSF is able to initiate
                      communications</h:i>].
              </h:p>
              <h:b>Application Note:</h:b>
              This PP-Module modifies this SFR to allow for the specification of any northbound, southbound, or east/west environmental components with which the TSF may implement protected communications. A conformant TOE may implement a distributed east/west configuration rather than the east/west entities being in the OE; in this case, the ST would define the TOE boundary as a distributed TOE in accordance with the NDcPP and use FPT_ITT.1 to define the interface between east/west distributed TOE components.
            </description>
            <no-change/>
          </base-sfr-spec>
        </section>
      </modified-sfrs>
      <!-- 5.1.2 Additional SFRs -->
      <additional-sfrs/>
      <con-toe>When this PP-Module is used to extend the NDcPP, the TOE type for the overall TOE is still a network device. The TOE boundary is simply extended to 
        include SDN controller functionality that is provided by the network device.</con-toe>
      <con-sec-prob>The threats defined by this PP-Module (see section 3.1) supplement those defined in the NDcPP as follows:</con-sec-prob>
      <con-obj/>
      <con-op-en>This PP-Module does not define any environmental objectives beyond those already defined in the NDcPP.</con-op-en>
      <con-mod ref="T.INSECURE_NORTHBOUND_API">This threat represents the same attack scenario as T.UNAUTHORISED_ADMINISTRATOR_ACCESS and T.UNTRUSTED_COMMUNICATION_CHANNELS, but
        applies to the north-south interface that is outside the scope originally defined by the Base-PP.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="nd-ftp-itc-1">This SFR modifies the Base-PP to define external interfaces particular to SDN controllers.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fau-gen-1-sdn">This SFR iterates the Base-PP to account for if the SDN controller has a different logging mechanism from the Base-PP use.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fdp-acc-1">This SFR defines access control policies that are specific to the PP-Module.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fdp-acf-1">This SFR defines access control policies to subjects and objects based on a set of rules and is specific to the PP-Module.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fmt-api-ext-1">This SFR defines API templates and the set of rules they must follow, which is specific to this PP-Module.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fmt-mof-1-sdn">This SFR iterates the Base-PP to add specific abilities of the API administrator to modify API function behavior.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fmt-smf-1-sdn">This SFR iterates the Base-PP to add management functions for API access control and validity, which is not defined in the Base-PP.</con-mod>
      <con-mod ref="fmt-smr-2-sdn">This SFR iterates the Base-PP to define specific roles for the API user and administrator, which is not defined in the Base-PP.</con-mod>
    </base-pp>
    <!-- 5.2 TOE Security Functional Requirements -->
    <man-sfrs>
      <section id="ss-audit-table" title="Auditable Events for Mandatory SFRs">
        <audit-table id="at-mandatory" table="mandatory"/>
      </section>
      <!-- 5.2.1 Class FAU: Security Audit -->
      <section title="Class FAU: Security Audit" id="man-fau">
        <!-- FAU_GEN.1/SDN Audit Data Generation (SDN) -->
        <f-component cc-id="fau_gen.1" id="fau-gen-1-sdn" name="Audit Data Generation (SDN)" iteration="SDN">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fau_gen-1-1_SDN">
            <title>
              The TSF shall
              <h:b>implement functionality</h:b>
              to generate audit data of the following
              <h:b>SDN</h:b>
              auditable events:
              <h:ol type="a">
                <h:li>Start-up and shutdown of the audit functions;</h:li>
                <h:li>All auditable events for [<h:i>not specified</h:i>] level of audit;</h:li>
                [<h:i><h:li>All unauthorized usage of all API endpoints, including create, read, update, and delete.</h:li>
                  <h:li>All authorized usage of all API endpoints, including create, read, update, and delete.</h:li>
                  <h:li>Full HTTP REST request parameters and values of any API requests sent to the SDN controller API.</h:li>
                  <h:li>All HTTP Response Codes returned from any HTTP API requests sent to the SDN controller API.</h:li>
                  <h:li>All error codes and error messages from usage of the API.</h:li>
                  <h:li>All auditable events for mandatory SFRs specified in <xref to="at-mandatory"/></h:li>
                </h:i>].
              </h:ol>
            </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fau_gen-1-2_SDN">
            <title>
              The TSF shall record within the
              <h:b>SDN</h:b>
              audit data at
            least the following information:
              <h:ol type="a">
                <h:li>Date and time of the event, type of event, subject identity, (if applicable) the outcome 
                (success or failure) of the event;</h:li>
                <h:li>
                  For each auditable event type, based on the auditable event definitions of the functional components 
                included in the PP, PP-Module, functional package, or ST, [<h:i>Additional Audit Record Contents as specified in <xref to="at-mandatory"/></h:i>].
                </h:li>
              </h:ol>
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              <h:p>This SFR mandates that audit data be generated for start-up and shutdown of the audit functions, which is a duplicate of FAU_GEN.1.1 in the Base-PP. If the TOE has one single audit mechanism, then the events used to conform to the Base-PP requirement also suffice here. Start-up and shutdown of the audit functions in the context of the SDN controller portion of the TOE only need to be logged separately if the SDN controller has a different logging mechanism from what the Base-PP uses.</h:p>
              <h:p>Note also that in many cases the start-up and shutdown of the audit functions cannot be forced on its own because the audit functions may be operational by default. In this case, logging for start-up and shutdown of the TOE itself is sufficient. The purpose of this part of the requirement is to ensure that a malicious user cannot disable auditing to evade detection of other malicious use of the TOE.</h:p>
              <h:p>The auditable events for the 'not specified' level of audit is intended to communicate that this PP-Module does not claim one of the pre-defined audit levels specified in CC Part 2; this is inherently satisfied by demonstrating that the TSF generates appropriate audit data for all events that are explicitly required by the PP-Module.</h:p>
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>
                <h:p>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS identifies the auditable events generated by the TOE, and that they include the auditable events specified in this SFR along with the required audit data. The evaluator shall also verify that the TSS identifies the mechanism used for generating audit events such that it can be determined whether the auditable events required by this PP-Module use the same audit mechanism as what the Base-PP requires for FAU_GEN.1 or there are alternate mechanisms that are used.</h:p>
                <h:p>The evaluator shall check that the requirement in the Base-PP to ensure that all auditable events can be transmitted to the operational environment via a secure channel is applicable to the entire TOE, even when PP-Modules are claimed. Therefore, if the TSF does have any audit mechanisms that are used specifically to generate audit records for this PP-Module's auditable events, the evaluator shall ensure that these mechanisms are discussed in the context of the Base-PP's requirements for protection of audit data in transit, and at rest if applicable.</h:p>
              </TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance identifies the auditable events that are generated by the TOE in support of this SFR and includes representative audit records of each event to demonstrate the format of each record. The evaluator shall verify that each sample audit record includes the fields required for each auditable event per FAU_GEN.1.2/SDN.</Guidance>
              <Tests>For each auditable event, the evaluator shall perform actions that are intended to cause a record of the event to be generated and verify that this occurs and that the required fields are present and accurate. If the audit mechanism used to generate any event differs from the mechanisms claimed in the Base-PP for FAU_GEN.1, the evaluator shall also perform the associated test activities for other claimed FAU class requirements to verify that the audit data is transferred to an external entity over the claimed trusted channel and that if audit data is stored locally, that it has the appropriate data at rest protections applied.</Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory"/>
        </f-component>
      </section>
      <!-- 5.2.2 Class FDP: User Data Protection -->
      <section title="Class FDP: User Data Protection" id="man-fdp">
        <!-- FDP_ACC.1 Subset Access Control -->
        <f-component cc-id="fdp_acc.1" id="fdp-acc-1" name="Subset Access Control">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fdp_acc-1-1">
            <title>The TSF shall enforce the [<h:i>API access control policy</h:i>] on [<h:i>all APIs used to access the TSF</h:i>].</title>
            <note role="application">The intent of this requirement is for the TOE to have a means to enforce access control on the invocation of APIs. The specific rules that comprise the policy itself are defined in FDP_ACF.1 below. It is not expected that the TOE have a construct explicitly called the "API access control policy," only that enforcement mechanisms exist to construct such a policy.</note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall examine the TSS to verify that it defines the TOE's API access control policy in terms of subjects (the users, groups, or machine entities that interact with APIs), objects (the APIs used to access the TSF, operations (invocation, modification, or some other function that can be done against the object), and any attributes that may govern the enforcement of the policy. Operations may also include the ability to limit the scope of particular API access; for example, a user may be authorized to invoke an API to configure one segment of a network but may be prohibited from configuring a different one.</TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall review the operational guidance to verify that it describes the TOE's API access control policy in terms of the subjects, objects, operations, and attributes specified in the ST, as well as which elements of this policy are enforced by default versus being configurable options. For any configurable elements of the API access control policy, the evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance describes how to perform this configuration.</Guidance>
              <Tests>There are no test activities for this component.</Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory"/>
        </f-component>
        <!-- FDP_ACF.1 Security Attribute-Based Access Control -->
        <f-component cc-id="fdp_acf.1" id="fdp-acf-1" name="Security Attribute-Based Access Control">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fdp_acf-1-1">
            <title>
              The TSF shall enforce the [<h:i>API access control policy</h:i>] to objects based on the
            following: [<h:i>supported operations that can be performed on or by API objects, the validity of the API call being issued, whether the API call is authorized based on the subject's role</h:i>].
            </title>
            <note role="application">The purpose of the API access control policy is to identify the API objects that are controlled by the TOE, the various types of access that can be performed against this object, and whether that access is permitted based on either the validity of the request itself or the entity requesting that access.</note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fdp_acf-1-2">
            <title>
              The TSF shall enforce the following rules to determine if an operation among controlled
            subjects and controlled objects is allowed: [<h:i>an API call that is valid with respect to an allowlisted API template can manipulate an object if allowing this manipulation has been configured</h:i>].
            </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fdp_acf-1-3">
            <title>
              The TSF shall explicitly authorize access of subjects to objects based on the following
            additional rules:
              <assignable>rules, based on security attributes, that explicitly allow access of subjects to objects</assignable>.
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              <h:p>The purpose of this requirement is to define an override mechanism where an allowlist may explicitly authorize some API access that would not otherwise be permitted by the API access control policy. It may be the case that no explicit denylist is supported and the policy as defined in FDP_ACF.1.2 always defines what is allowed and denied with no exceptions. If this is the case, the ST author may complete the assignment with "no additional rules."</h:p>
              <h:p>This is intended to support the potential for operations that may be authorized on the basis of permissions; it is not intended to authorize API calls that are invalid regardless of permissions.</h:p>
            </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fdp_acf-1-4">
            <title>
              The TSF shall explicitly deny access of subjects to objects based on the following additional
            rules:
              <assignable>rules, based on security attributes, that explicitly deny access of subjects to objects</assignable>.
            </title>
            <note role="application">The purpose of this requirement is to define an override mechanism where a denylist may explicitly prohibit some API access that would not otherwise be permitted by the API access control policy. It may be the case that no explicit denylist is supported and the policy as defined in FDP_ACF.1.2 always defines what is allowed and denied with no exceptions. If this is the case, the ST author may complete the assignment with "no additional rules."</note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS describes the TOE's API access control policy in sufficient detail to conclude, for each API, the operations that can be performed on or by the API, and the authorization required to perform those operations. If the TOE implements explicit allowlisting or denylisting to override any default or configurable policy rules, the evaluator shall verify that these are described. In cases where multiple contradictory rules exist to define authorizations, the evaluator shall verify that the TSS describes the precedence in which these rules are prioritized.</TSS>
              <Guidance>
                <h:p>The evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance identifies, for each API, the mechanism that exist to control access to that API, and how to perform such configuration. The evaluator shall also verify that the operational guidance defines any default policy rules that may exist. The evaluator shall also verify that the operational guidance describes the ordering of rule processing such that it is clear what behavior is followed in the event that multiple contradictory rules exist.  If this is configurable (e.g., because rules are enforced in a configurable priority order), the evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance provides instructions on how to perform this configuration.</h:p>
                <h:p>Additionally, the evaluator shall verify that each API is defined in terms of the operations that can be performed by or against them and the valid parameters for these operations.</h:p>
              </Guidance>
              <Tests>
                The evaluator shall perform the following tests:
                <testlist>
                  <test>Default policy test: The evaluator shall review the operational guidance to determine what default policy rules (if any) are enforced by the TOE. For each such rule, the evaluator shall attempt to access the TOE's APIs in a manner prohibited by the default policy rule and verify that access is prohibited as expected. The evaluator shall then access these APIs as a subject with sufficient authorization and verify that the requested access is permitted.</test>
                  <test>Configured policy test: For each API policy element that is configurable (e.g., by determining what users or groups are authorized to access a particular API), the evaluator shall follow the instructions in the operational guidance to configure positive and negative test scenarios where access is allowed and rejected. The evaluator shall then access the TOE as subjects that are and are not authorized to access the particular API, and verify that the TSF allows or rejects the access as configured.</test>
                  <test>Contradictory policy test: For each situation identified in the ST where contradictory rules may exist (e.g., an operation is both allowlisted and denylisted), the evaluator shall apply these contradictory rules to the API, attempt to access the API in such a way that their authorization to do so is ambiguous (i.e., one rule permits the action and one rejects it), and verify that whether or not the attempt is authorized resolves in the manner specified in the TSS. If this functionality is configurable (e.g., the rules are enforced in a set order), the evaluator shall follow the steps necessary to change the priority of their enforcement, re-attempt the same access, and verify that the attempt resolves in the manner specified by the new configuration.</test>
                  <test>Validity test: For each API, the evaluator shall connect a network traffic generator to the API and configure it to inject bad data into API requests that follow operations to legitimately assume a role that is authorized to invoke the API (in other words, attempt to perform an invalid operation as a valid subject). "Bad data" in this case is determined by the operational guidance's definition for what values are acceptable for the parameters of a particular API. In all cases, attempts to invoke an API using invalid data shall fail.</test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory"/>
        </f-component>
      </section>
      <!-- 5.2.3 Class FMT: Security Management -->
      <section title="Class FMT: Security Management" id="man-fmt">
        <ext-comp-def title="Management of API Behavior" fam-id="FMT_API_EXT">
          <fam-behavior>This family defines requirements for management of API behavior.</fam-behavior>
        </ext-comp-def>
        <!-- FMT_API_EXT.1 Management of API Behavior -->
        <f-component cc-id="fmt_api_ext.1" id="fmt-api-ext-1" name="Management of API Behavior">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <comp-lev>requires the TSF to define API templates and determine whether they meet specified rules.</comp-lev>
          <management>There are no management activities foreseen.</management>
          <audit>The following actions should be auditable if FAU_GEN Security audit data generation is included in the PP, PP-Module, functional package, or ST: <h:ul><h:li>Successful and failed definition of API template.</h:li></h:ul></audit>
          <dependencies>FCS_CKM.6 Timing and Event of Cryptographic Key Destruction</dependencies>
          <f-element id="fmt_api_ext-1-1">
            <title>
              The TSF shall provide the ability to define the following API templates
              <assignable>list of API templates</assignable>
              against the following API objects
              <assignable>list of API objects</assignable>.
            </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fmt_api_ext-1-2">
            <title>The TSF shall permit API templates to be defined if they meet the following specified rules:  <assignable>rules determining allowable templates</assignable>.</title>
            <note role="application">
              The intent of this requirement is to require the ST to define API endpoints that the SDN controller exposes for administering the SDN controller itself, and for inducing the SDN
              controller to administer the network devices that it manages. This could include, but is not limited to, APIs for the following behavior:
              <h:ul>
                <h:li>Endpoints that modify the SDN controller's own configuration, including any changes to:<h:ul><h:li>System settings</h:li> <h:li>Operational parameters</h:li></h:ul></h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that cause the SDN controller to modify network configurations, such as:<h:ul><h:li>Routing settings</h:li> <h:li>Switching settings</h:li></h:ul></h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that change the SDN controller's power state, including:<h:ul><h:li>Power on and off</h:li> <h:li>Reboot operations</h:li></h:ul></h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that cause the SDN controller to change the power state of managed network devices, including:<h:ul><h:li>Power on and off</h:li> <h:li>Reboot operations</h:li></h:ul></h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that modify the SDN controller's security or hardening settings, including:<h:ul><h:li>Security policies</h:li> <h:li>Hardening configurations</h:li></h:ul></h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that cause the SDN controller to modify security or hardening settings on managed network devices.</h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that change authentication or authorization controls on the SDN controller.</h:li>
                <h:li>Endpoints that change authentication or authorization controls on managed network devices.</h:li>
              </h:ul>
              <h:br/>
              <h:br/>
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS identifies the API templates that can be applied to API objects, consistent with the claims made in FMT_API_EXT.1.1. The evaluator shall verify that the TSS describes any rules that are enforced on the definition of API templates.</TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall examine the operational guidance to verify that the guidance identifies the API templates that can be applied to API objects as well as the administrative permissions necessary on the TOE to apply these. If additional templates may be defined per FMT_API_EXT.1.2, the evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance specifies the rules that are applied to allowable templates, both in terms of syntax (i.e., what constitutes a valid template) and authorization (i.e., what role or other attribute permits an administrator to perform this function).</Guidance>
              <Tests>
                The evaluator shall perform the following tests:
                <testlist>
                  <test>For each API template that can be applied to API objects, the evaluator shall verify that a sufficiently privileged administrator on the TOE is able to apply the template to the supported objects.</test>
                  <test>[Conditional: The TOE supports the definition of additional templates] The evaluator shall follow the operational guidance to define a new API template that is consistent with the defined rules for both syntax and authorization and verify that the template is successfully defined.</test>
                  <test>[Conditional: The TOE supports the definition of additional templates] If the ability to define additional templates is restricted based on administrative role or other attribute, the evaluator shall access the TOE as an insufficiently privileged administrator to define new API templates and verify that there is no mechanism by which a new template can be defined.</test>
                  <test>[Conditional: The TOE supports the definition of additional templates] The evaluator shall access the TOE with an administrator account that is sufficiently privileged to define additional API templates and verify that a template is not created if it is invalid with respect to its syntax or composition.</test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory">
            <audit-event-descr>Successful and failed definition or modification of API template</audit-event-descr>
            <audit-event-info>Identification of template (if successful)</audit-event-info>
          </audit-event>
        </f-component>
        <!-- FMT_MOF.1/SDN Management of Functions Behavior (SDN) -->
        <f-component cc-id="fmt_mof.1" id="fmt-mof-1-sdn" name="Management of Functions Behavior (SDN)" iteration="SDN">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fmt_mof-1-1_SDN">
            <title>
              The TSF shall restrict the ability to [<h:i>modify the behaviour of</h:i>] the functions [<h:i>API access function as defined by FDP_ACC.1, API validity function as defined by FMT_API_EXT.1</h:i>] to [<h:i>API administrator</h:i>].
            </title>
            <note role="application">The restriction of modifying API access and validity functions to the API administrator is intended to imply that the API user does not have the ability to modify API functions. The API user role having read-only access to these functions is not precluded by this requirement, as this requirement only relates to the ability to modify the behavior of the API.</note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall examine the TSS to verify that it identifies the API access and API validity functions provided by the TOE and verify that an API administrator is the only subject that is authorized to modify the behavior of these functions (e.g., by determining the subjects that are authorized to access a particular function). Note that the "API administrator" role is a necessary but not sufficient condition to be authorized to perform management functions. If the TSF implements more granular controls (e.g., different API administrators have access to different sets of functions based on role or other subject attribute), the evaluator shall verify that the TSS includes sufficient data to determine that it fully describes the authorizations needed to perform management functions against the TOE's APIs.</TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall examine the operational guidance to verify that it describes the TOE's claimed management functions and the privileges required to execute those functions.</Guidance>
              <Tests>For each claimed management function, the evaluator shall access the TOE as a legitimate user that lacks privileges to perform the function, attempt to perform the function, and verify that it fails (or that there is no mechanism by which an attempt can even be made). If multiple conditions define the ability to perform the function, the evaluator shall repeat this activity as needed to verify that the absence of each condition is sufficient to prevent the execution of the function. The evaluator shall then access the TOE with all necessary authorities to perform the function and verify that it is successful.</Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory"/>
        </f-component>
        <!-- FMT_SMF.1/SDN Specification of Management Functions (SDN) -->
        <f-component cc-id="fmt_smf.1" id="fmt-smf-1-sdn" name="Specification of Management Functions (SDN)" iteration="SDN">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fmt_smf-1-1_SDN">
            <title>
              The TSF shall be capable of performing the following management functions: [<h:i>API access control as defined by FDP_ACF.1, API validity as defined by FMT_API_EXT.1</h:i>].
            </title>
            <note role="application">API access control refers to configuring the allowlist for the permitted API templates. API validity refers to the ability to defining the templates for how API calls must be performed to access API objects. The intent of this requirement is for the TSF to have the ability to define both when and how a given API can be invoked.</note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS identifies each management function that can be performed by the TOE, whether that is to execute a given function as defined by FDP_ACC.1 or to modify the behavior of how the function is executed as defined by FMT_MOF.1/SDN.</TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall examine the operational guidance to verify that it provides instructions on how to perform each management function specified in this SFR.</Guidance>
              <Tests>For each specified management function, the evaluator shall access the TOE as a subject that is sufficiently privileged to perform the function, execute the function, and verify that executing the function has the intended effect.</Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory"/>
        </f-component>
        <!-- FMT_SMR.2/SDN Restrictions on Security Roles (SDN) -->
        <f-component cc-id="fmt_smr.2" id="fmt-smr-2-sdn" name="Restrictions on Security Roles (SDN)" iteration="SDN">
          <consistency-rationale/>
          <f-element id="fmt_smr-2-1_SDN">
            <title>
              The TSF shall maintain the roles: [<h:i>API user, API administrator</h:i>].
            </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fmt_smr-2-2_SDN">
            <title>The TSF shall be able to associate users with roles.</title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fmt_smr-2-3_SDN">
            <title>The TSF shall ensure that the conditions [<h:i>API user and API administrator roles cannot be held simultaneously</h:i>] are satisfied.</title>
            <note role="application">The Base-PP defines FMT_SMR.2 for the "Security Administrator" role that must be available on a network device in general. This iteration supplements that by making sure that API user and API administrator roles exist for SDN functionality but are logically separated. The security administrator as defined by that SFR may also be an API administrator as defined by this iteration, or management of general security functionality may be separated from API administration such that they are granted by different roles.</note>
            <aactivity>
              <TSS>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS defines the roles available to subjects on the TOE, and that these may be categorized into API user and API administrator roles. The TOE does not need to implement roles with these specified names, but based on the description of the TOE's privilege model it should be clear how the roles and permissions on the TOE map to the concept of an API user that may only execute functions and an API administrator that has the ability to modify the behavior of those functions.</TSS>
              <Guidance>The evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance identifies the administrative roles available for subjects on the TOE and the mechanism by which subjects are associated with roles. The evaluator shall also verify that this identifies how the API user and API administrator role cannot be held simultaneously (e.g., because a user may only have one role and these are defined as two separate roles; because write privilege and execute privilege cannot be held by the same subject for any given API).</Guidance>
              <Tests>The evaluator shall follow the operational guidance to associate subjects with the roles defined by the TOE to verify that subjects may be given an API user role or an API administrator role. The evaluator shall attempt to assign a subject to both roles and verify that this fails or that no mechanism exists to attempt this.</Tests>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <audit-event table="mandatory">
            <audit-event-descr>Assignment of user to role</audit-event-descr>
            <audit-event-info>Identification of subject and assigned role</audit-event-info>
          </audit-event>
        </f-component>
      </section>
    </man-sfrs>
    <mod-sars/>
    <opt-sfrs/>
    <sel-sfrs/>
    <obj-sfrs/>
    <impl-dep-sfrs/>
  </sec:Security_Requirements>
  <bibliography>
    <entry id="bibNDcPP">
      <tag>NDcPP</tag>
      <description>
        <h:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/protectionprofiles/524">collaborative Protection Profile for Network Devices, Version 4.0, December 22, 2025</h:a>
      </description>
    </entry>
  </bibliography>
</Module>
